<?xml version="1.0"?>
<resume xmlns="https://tylersommer.pro" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="https://tylersommer.pro data.xsd">
    <name>Tyler Sommer</name>
    <phone>(760) 576-5846</phone>
    <email>contact@tylersommer.pro</email>

    <title>Software Engineer</title>
    <title>Father</title>
    <title>Tinkerer</title>
    <title>Geek</title>
    <description>Fifteen years of professional software engineering experience in demanding, fast-paced environments. Focus primarily in backend systems: infrastructure, integrations, and distributed and embedded systems. Strengths include problem solving, communication, technical writing, and systems operations. Passionate about open source software.</description>

    <profile>
        <section>Born and raised in the suburbs outside Salt Lake City, Utah, I got my first computer around 1998 when I was just ten years old. It was a beige Windows 95 machine and it opened doors to someplace magical.</section>
        <section>A year or so later, I received my own copy of Microsoft Frontpage 2000 as a gift. I recall building many terrible, terrible websites dedicated to Pokémon and Dragonball Z. Meager beginnings to what would become a successful career in software engineering.</section>
        <section>I landed my first professional coding gig in 2008, integrating landing pages with CRMs and CRMs with payment processors. Then, building a payment processor itself. A decade later and I'm building resilient, distributed systems that operate on a global scale.</section>
        <section>Computing is a major passion of mine. I am constantly fascinated by all aspects of software engineering. I'm always in search of knowledge and application. These days, I spend most of my time learning how to be a dad. Otherwise, you'll find me coding, tinkering, and learning new things... or watching Star Trek.</section>
    </profile>

    <experience>
        <position>
            <company>Minim</company>
            <title>Senior Full-Stack Engineer</title>
            <location>Manchester, NH</location>
            <from>2018</from>
            <to>2023</to>
            <description>
                <section>Expanded capabilities and improved stability across diverse projects ranging from embedded C codebases to cloud-based Ruby on Rails, Rust, and TypeScript applications. Developed and supported infrastructure-as-code deployed around the globe in AWS and Azure.</section>
                <section>Developed, launched, and scaled cloud hosted router agent geared toward network monitoring and security. Worked closely with customer-facing teams to support customer deployments and develop institutional knowledgebase for available platforms.</section>
                <section>Launched open source version of embedded router agent and developed cloud-side tools and documentation to manage open source installations. Added desktop linux support for the agent and launched Raspberry Pi based installation support.</section>
            </description>
        </position>

        <position>
            <company>Rakuten Marketing</company>
            <title>Software Engineer</title>
            <location>Midvale, UT</location>
            <from>2016</from>
            <to>2018</to>
            <description>
                <section>Responsible for maintenance, modernization, and new feature development for a distributed ad-serving platform deployed globally. Developed automated integrated testing framework to efficiently test the entire platform at scale.</section>
                <section>Built new and improved existing Hadoop, Hive, and Spark processes and related tooling for processing large amounts of data. Designed and developed Spark Streaming applications and related tooling.</section>
            </description>
        </position>

        <position>
            <company>Pronexis</company>
            <title>Senior Developer</title>
            <location>Spanish Fork, UT</location>
            <from>2015</from>
            <to>2016</to>
            <description>
                <section>Designed and built business and customer management software for service-based industries like pest control and lawncare. Developed customer, truck routing, invoicing, and sales team management systems.</section>
                <section>Responsible for maintaining and improving existing Symfony code-base. Implemented unit testing, integration testing, and continuous integration processes.</section>
            </description>
        </position>

        <position>
            <company>Terramar Labs</company>
            <title>Lead Developer</title>
            <location>San Diego, CA</location>
            <from>2012</from>
            <to>2015</to>
            <description>
                <section>Built software for small to medium businesses to help manage their internal processes and bottom line. Developed reporting and analytics tools, mobile kiosk applications, and web services.</section>
                <section>Engineered and contributed to many open source applications leveraged by Terramar Labs to manage code packages, code review, and payment processing.</section>
            </description>
        </position>

        <position>
            <company>PayRoll Innovations</company>
            <title>Lead Developer</title>
            <location>South Jordan, UT</location>
            <from>2010</from>
            <to>2012</to>
            <description>
                <section>Architected a payday advance loan processing system integrated with card issuing platforms. Implemented risk scoring algorithm to automatically qualify potential loan applicants based on various factors.</section>
                <section>Responsible for the maintenance of a small server cluster including primary and fail-over web and database servers.</section>
            </description>
        </position>

        <position>
            <company>NovaCare</company>
            <title>Developer / IT Manager</title>
            <location>Murray, UT</location>
            <from>2008</from>
            <to>2010</to>
            <description>
                <section>Integrated landing pages and various CRM platforms and payment processors. Maintained and improved legacy Visual Basic and Classic ASP fulfillment system. Implemented automation tools for managing high-volume printing and returns processing.</section>
                <section>Managed company-wide IT infrastructure and a small team of IT support personnel.</section>
            </description>
        </position>

        <extra kind="hobby">Maintainer of multiple open source projects in free time. Responsible for libraries and applications for payment processing, API consumption, templating, software package management, and pseudo-interactive chat participants.</extra>
        <extra kind="hobby">Built Arduino-based wireless transponder and touchscreen receiver for remotely tracking model rockets. Integrated a number of sensors including GPS, transmitting the readings at regular intervals to remote handheld receiver.</extra>
        <extra kind="contract">Designed and developed proprietary advertising tracking platform with single point of integration pixel placement and extensive reporting functionality.</extra>
        <extra kind="contract">Expanded feature-set on a proprietary CRM/CMS system with a primary focus on fulfillment integration and and e-commerce reporting. Worked with small team of developers to improve performance and scalability.</extra>
        <extra kind="contract">Built proof-of-concept photo mosaic generating app for iOS. Finished prototype was delivered and presented to several high profile clients with great reception.</extra>
    </experience>

    <projects>
        <project>
            <name>Packages</name>
            <blurb>Composer package management made simple.</blurb>
            <description>
                <section>Packages is a private Composer repository manager with GitHub and GitLab integration. Originally developed for Terramar Labs' internal work, we open sourced the project and maintain it to this day.</section>
                <section>This project is a neat example of using webhooks to integrate with external services as well as a decently powerful continuous integration/deployment platform.</section>
            </description>
            <link href="https://github.com/terramar-labs/packages" icon="fab fa-github">GitHub</link>
            <link href="http://docs.terramarlabs.com" icon="fas fa-book">Documentation</link>
        </project>

        <project>
            <name>Stick</name>
            <blurb>Golang port of the Twig templating engine.</blurb>
            <description>
                <section>Stick is a Go language port of the Twig templating engine. Stick supports all Twig syntax though full Twig-compatibility is incomplete. Stick itself is feature complete and used in many of my personal projects.</section>
                <section>This project started out from a need for a more powerful templating language than what was provided at the time by the Go standard library.</section>
            </description>
            <link href="https://github.com/tyler-sommer/stick" icon="fab fa-github">GitHub</link>
        </project>

        <project>
            <name>transpond</name>
            <blurb>GPS tracker and handset for model rockets.</blurb>
            <description>
                <section>transpond is an Arduino application consisting of two parts: the transponder and the handset. The transponder is placed in the payload section of a model rocket and transmits data continuously to the handset. Sensors include GPS, Accel/Gyro/Magneto, voltage, and temperature.</section>
            </description>
            <link href="https://github.com/veonik/transpond" icon="fab fa-github">GitHub</link>
        </project>

        <project>
            <name>squircy3</name>
            <blurb>The penultimate IRC bot</blurb>
            <description>
                <section>squircy3 is a platform for building event based applications, such as chat bots. Functionality is based around plugins, which include support for Discord, IRC, and a built-in JavaScript runtime with full interop between JS and Go, thanks to the incredible github.com/dop251/goja project, a little babel.js, and a bunch of fairy dust.</section>
            </description>
            <link href="https://github.com/veonik/squircy3" icon="fab fa-github">GitHub</link>
        </project>

        <project>
            <name>squirssi</name>
            <blurb>An irssi-inspired terminal IRC client</blurb>
            <description>
                <section>squirssi is an IRC client implemented as squircy3 plugins. Started as a proof-of-concept, squirssi is now very usable as a real IRC client.. if a terminal-based client is your thing.</section>
            </description>
            <link href="https://github.com/veonik/squirssi" icon="fab fa-github">GitHub</link>
        </project>

        <project>
            <name>squIRCy2</name>
            <blurb>An IRC bot that is scriptable with javascript!</blurb>
            <description>
                <section>squIRCy2 is an IRC bot written in Go that embeds a javascript VM that allows userland scripting via the filesystem or a web interface. Now deprecated in favor of squircy3, this project still holds a special place in my heart and deserves a mention.</section>
            </description>
            <link href="https://github.com/veonik/squircy2" icon="fab fa-github">GitHub</link>
            <link href="https://squircy.com" icon="fas fa-book">Documentation</link>
        </project>

        <project>
            <name>MOTKI</name>
            <blurb>A suite of apps tailored for corp management in EVE online.</blurb>
            <description>
                <section>The MOTKI project as a whole is a suite of software designed around managing a corporation in the video game EVE Online. MOTKI is a web application that integrates with many different data sources using the EVE Single Sign-On API to gather detailed information.</section>
            </description>
            <link href="https://github.com/motki" icon="fab fa-github">GitHub</link>
        </project>

        <project>
            <name>VeonikBlogBundle</name>
            <blurb>A Symfony bundle providing CMS and blog functionality.</blurb>
            <description>
                <section>VeonikBlogBundle is a Symfony bundle that has all the necessary functionality for quickly building a blog or CMS. Features include WYSIWYG editing, dynamic menus, user accounts, file uploading, and syntax highlighting for code snippets.</section>
                <section>VeonikBlogBundle is largely what powers my personal blog, Tyler Sommer dot com.</section>
            </description>
            <link href="https://github.com/veonik/VeonikBlogBundle" icon="fab fa-github">GitHub</link>
        </project>

        <project>
            <name>Tyler Sommer dot com</name>
            <blurb>My personal website.</blurb>
            <description>
                <section>Tyler Sommer dot com is my most successful and longest running attempt at maintaining a blog. The application is built using Symfony and Doctrine, but still running on Symfony 2.8 and Bootstrap 2 it is starting to show signs of age.</section>
            </description>
            <link href="https://github.com/tyler-sommer/TylerSommerdotcom" icon="fab fa-github">GitHub</link>
            <link href="https://tylersommer.com" icon="fas fa-bookmark">Tyler Sommer dot com</link>
        </project>
    </projects>

    <qualifications>
        <attribute type="language">Ruby</attribute>
        <attribute type="language">Go</attribute>
        <attribute type="language">JavaScript</attribute>
        <attribute type="language">TypeScript</attribute>
        <attribute type="language">SQL</attribute>
        <attribute type="language">Bash</attribute>
        <attribute type="language">RouterOS Script</attribute>
        <attribute type="language">C</attribute>
        <attribute type="language">PHP</attribute>
        <attribute type="language" rusty="true">Rust</attribute>
        <attribute type="language" rusty="true">Java</attribute>
        <attribute type="language" rusty="true">Scala</attribute>
        <attribute type="language" rusty="true">Swift</attribute>
        <attribute type="language" rusty="true">Objective-C</attribute>
        <attribute type="language" rusty="true">C++</attribute>
        <attribute type="language" rusty="true">Haskell</attribute>
        <attribute type="language" rusty="true">Python</attribute>
        <attribute type="language" rusty="true">C#</attribute>
        <attribute type="platform">AWS</attribute>
        <attribute type="platform" rusty="true">GCP</attribute>
        <attribute type="platform">Azure</attribute>
        <attribute type="platform">Linux</attribute>
        <attribute type="platform">OpenWrt</attribute>
        <attribute type="platform">MikroTik</attribute>
        <attribute type="platform">Docker</attribute>
        <attribute type="platform">Kubernetes</attribute>
        <attribute type="platform">Terraform</attribute>
        <attribute type="platform">Ansible</attribute>
        <attribute type="platform">PostgreSQL</attribute>
        <attribute type="platform">MySQL</attribute>
        <attribute type="platform" rusty="true">Apache Spark</attribute>
        <attribute type="platform" rusty="true">Hadoop</attribute>
        <attribute type="platform" rusty="true">Hive</attribute>
        <attribute type="platform" rusty="true">Cassandra</attribute>
    </qualifications>

    <links>
        <social href="https://github.com/tyler-sommer" icon="fab fa-github">GitHub</social>
        <social href="https://tylersommer.com" icon="fas fa-blog">Blog</social>
        <social href="https://defcon.social/@syncreticidiot" icon="fab fa-mastodon">Mastodon</social>
        <social href="https://twitter.com/syncreticidiot" icon="fab fa-twitter">Twitter</social>
        <social href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/tylersommer/" icon="fab fa-linkedin">LinkedIn</social>
        <social href="https://tylersommer.pro/print" icon="fas fa-print">Print Version</social>
    </links>
</resume>
